<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The schysmatical puritan A sermon preached at Witney concerning the lawfulnesse of church-authority, for ordaining, and commanding of rites, and ceremonies, to beautifie the Church. By Giles Widdowes rector of St Martins church in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Widdowes, Giles, 1558?-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120720</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855914</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855914</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21422</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15304)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21422)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1048:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The schysmatical puritan A sermon preached at Witney concerning the lawfulnesse of church-authority, for ordaining, and commanding of rites, and ceremonies, to beautifie the Church. By Giles Widdowes rector of St Martins church in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Widdowes, Giles, 1558?-1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By John Lichfield] for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Most copies have an "i" hand-stamped over the "y" in "schysmatical" on the title page; a few copies apparently are altered in MS. (STC).</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The authority of the Church.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:21422:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21422:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>THE SCHYSMATICAL</hi> P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RITAN.</p>
            <p>A <hi>SERMON PREACHED AT WIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEY concerning the lawfulneſſe of</hi> Church-Authority, for ordaining, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Rites, and Ceremonies, to beautifie the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By GILES WIDDOWES Rector of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. MARTINS Church in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>TITVS.</hi> 1. 15.</bibl>
               <p>Vnto the pure all things are pure, but vnto them, that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, and vnbeleeving, nothing is pure; but their Minde, and Conſcience are defiled.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at Oxford for the Author. 1630.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21422:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21422:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS GRACIOVS LADY, KATHARINE, DVTCHES of BVCKINGHAM HER GRACE, all health, proſperity, and ſalvation through Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Mportunitie of friends hath with vn-anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſwaſions conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me, to imprint this Sermon: becauſe an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant zeale of ſome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty spirits, would cry downe the lawfull Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the true Doctrine, and diſcipline of our Reformed Church. I therefore deſire your Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:21422:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> favour moſt earneſtly, to accept theſe my firſt fruits, ſacrific'd on the Preſſe; and to wiſh them ſafe protection. My oblig'd duty directs, and neceſſitates me, to be thankefull vnto you, for your ſpeciall favours beyond my deſert, to dedicate myſelfe, and theſe my orthodoxe labours to ſo good, and Gracious a Lady. The Lord Crowne your merits with ſpirituall, and temporall bleſſings for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, and that for the hearty prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt humble ſervant and Chaplaine GILES WIDDOWES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21422:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE PVRITAN.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is your practiſe, to run from the Church. Iam ſorry, that ſo learned, and ſo holy men, as you would ſeeme to be, doe want true Chriſtian patience, to heare orthodox holy doctrine. But let me intreat you, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand me this one time. I hope it will be for your edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying. This is my prayer vnto Almighty God through Ieſus Chriſt. My buſineſſe with you is the <hi>Puritan:</hi> whoſe name diſtinguiſh'd, whoſe eſſence re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d'red in the very property, and whoſe ſeverall kinds eſſentially differing, I giue into your owne hands, that you may ſee, and learne true Reformation.</p>
            <p>Concerning the name <hi>(Puritan)</hi> it is ambiguous, and ſo it is fallacious. For ſome good men are called <hi>Puritans:</hi> and they are <hi>Puritans</hi> indeed. They are pure in heart, and ſo bleſſed, that they ſhall ſee God. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 8. And ſome evill men are called <hi>Puritans,</hi> who deſire to ſeeme to be iuſt, and holy; but in their doctrine, and diſcipline, they are the vnderminers of our True, Proteſtant, Reformed Church. Are you
<pb facs="tcp:21422:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> angry, becauſe I tell you the truth. <hi>Be angry but ſin not,</hi> and I will tell you, the eſſentiall definition of this fallacious <hi>Puritan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Puritan</hi> is a Proteſtant Non-Conformiſt. A Proteſtant, this is his Genus, his kinde of being. A Non-Conformiſt: this is his differentia, his eſſentiall difference, his eſſentiall Qualitie. A <hi>Puritan</hi> is a kind of Proteſtant. For he wilbe tryed by the Scriptures concerning his faith, and his Chriſtian morall life, ſo farre as his Spirit will endure the text. But the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures deduceable ſence in Eſſentials, Eſſentiates, Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, Finals, Subiects, Effects, and their Modalities, being oppoſite to their tenets, confounds this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, and overthrowes his Chaire: but he aſham'd to forſake his ſeducing profeſſion a long time vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently clamarous, taketh faſt hold only on the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and chapter of the text. So then this <hi>Puritan</hi> is a ſullen fallacie of the Reformed Church: being confuted, he will not learne to turne: ſtill he is pure, not really, but in his owne ſuppoſe. The Lord graunt him grace to reforme.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Puritan</hi> is a Non-Conformiſt. For he is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitely ſet, a Contradictiſt to the Scriptures deduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſence in three things. The firſt is the 39 Articles of our Churches Reformed faith. The ſecond is our Common Praier-booke. The third is the Canons of our Church. And yet the doctrine of the Articles, the faith of the common prayers, and the lawfulneſſe of the Canons, are contained in the deduce-able ſence of holy Scriptures. The Articles of our Reformed
<pb facs="tcp:21422:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> Churches ſaith, which he oppoſeth, are theſe: the 3. 6. 9. 16. 17. 20. 21. 23. 26. 27. 33. 35. 36. 37. 38. 39. This is proved in the ſeverall kindes of this irregular ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turiſt. The praiers in the common prayer-booke, which he contradicts (being collected, and tranſlated out of the Maſſe-booke, yet corrected, and purged from groſſe errors) thoſe ſelected prayers he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth every one, becauſe they were thence collected. The Abſolution he diſliketh, becauſe he makes a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, whether the congregation did faithfully, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitently confeſſe their ſinnes. The Lords prayer hee will not ſay, becauſe hee will make a praier like to the Lords praier. <hi>Nunc dimittis, &amp;c:</hi> hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, becauſe he will not any praier, or hymne, but ſuch as hee thinkes fit according to his owne will. The Letanie he ſaith is compoſed of coniuring, and ſwearing, and of vnneceſſarie and vnlawfull In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations. The collect on Trinitie Sunday, he ſaith is compoſed of an Impoſſibilitie. And that the laſt collect but one read at holy Communion is compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of vntruths. He is ill-diſpoſed., oppoſitely affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt prayers at Chriſtnings, Confirmations, and Burialls.</p>
            <p>I make anſwere thus. To pronounce, He pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and abſolveth all them, which truely repent, and vnfainedly belieue; is the actuall duetie of Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Prieſts, and ſo good a duetie is no ſinne. Miniſters (muſt) ſay the Lords prayer. The Lord hath ſaid it. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. 2. And they muſt make their praiers accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the forme of the Lords prayer. It is the text,
<pb facs="tcp:21422:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> they muſt vſe no vaine babling: their forme of praier muſt be effectuall, not vaine; briefe, not ſtuffed with tautologies, and iterations. Read <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. 8. 9. God did regard vs with a Saviour, in that he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the Bleſſed Virgin with a Sonne, and a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, therefore we ſay the Magnificat. Wee ſhalbe ſaved by the ſame faith, as old Simeon was, therefore we ſay <hi>Nunc dimittis.</hi> In the Letanie we pray to bee delivered from ſinne, and puniſhment. And how muſt Chriſtians pray for to bee delivered, but by Chriſts agonie, and bloody ſweat, &amp;c? And is this ſwearing, or coniuring? Is praying in the Winter, to be delivered from thunder, and lightning, vnneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie? Lightning, and thunder are Gods ſecret iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: he may afflict ſinners with them in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: though naturally ſummer bee the time for thoſe terrifying Meteors: but becauſe they are Gods ſecret iudgements, therefore we pray alwaies for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Is praying for theeues, and whores vnlawfull, the one being included in all men, travayling by land, or by water; the other being included in all women labouring with child? Our Saviour ſaith, that his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father <hi>is mercifull to the iuſt, and vniuſt,</hi> and that all Gods people muſt be ſo mercifull <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 48. &amp;c: And S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>doe good vnto all. Gal.</hi> 6. 10: and therefore we muſt pray for all. On Trinity Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day we pray to be delivered from all adverſity; and it is thus in the Lords praier: <hi>Deliuer vs from all evill:</hi> And ſhall we not pray, as the Lord hath taught vs? In the laſt Collect but one at the holy Communion,
<pb facs="tcp:21422:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> wee Confeſſe our vnworthines, and blindnes: And whereſoever ſinne is inherent, and a fighter, there muſt be <hi>neceſsitate cauſae,</hi> (ſin being an actuall cauſe,) an vnworthyneſſe of Gods favour, and blind igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; not in the neceſſary precepts of ſaith, but in Contingents, with what particular bleſſing, when, where, and how God will bleſſe ſinners. Prayers at Baptiſme doe regenerate: though you denie this. Tis the text: <hi>Aske, and you ſhall haue.</hi> To pray is to <hi>Aske.</hi> To be Regenerate is to <hi>haue.</hi> The bleſſed Apoſtles did confirme the Churches, which they before had converted. <hi>Act.</hi> 14. 22. <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 32. <hi>For confirmation is a Principle of the doctrine of Chriſt</hi> next to baptiſme. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 1. 2. Therefore S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> did pray &amp; impoſe hands to confirme the Church with the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 17. And little Children being more weake in the ſtate of Grace, then ſuch Converts, muſt neceſſarily be confirmed by the Biſhop, the Apoſtle of the Dioceſſe; though not by miraculous, <hi>yet by ſeaven, of the holy Ghosts gifts.</hi> We muſt pray for the dead. <hi>Thy kingdome come.</hi> Oh Lord raiſe the dead priſoners in the graue. And herein we pray for their ſoules, and bodies. God be with them, to comfort their ſoules deprived of their bodies; I ſay to comfort them with haſt'ning the Re-vnion, and the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate ioy of ſoule and body. Thus the Primitiue Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: <hi>Iunius, B. Bilſon, Mornay, Chameirus.</hi> This is not to defend Purgatory, but the receaued anſwere againſt Purgatory.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being thus anſwered; obſerue that
<pb facs="tcp:21422:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> this <hi>Puritan</hi> would obſtinately caſt out of the Church, <hi>Gods ſauing mercy, ſaving hope, ſaving cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and the ſeauen guifts of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> And what then is his religion, but faction? <hi>But marke thoſe, that cauſe diuiſion in the Church, contrary to the doctrine, which you haue receiued. For they, that are ſuch, ſerue not the Lord Ieſus, but their owne bellies; and with faire ſpeech, and flattering, deceiue the hearts of the ſimple. Rom.</hi> 16. 17. 18.</p>
            <p>The third thing, in which this <hi>Puritan</hi> is Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt, is the Canons of our reformed Church. Theſe, 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12. 13. 14. 15. 24. 29. 30. 31. 48. 49. 54. 55. 56. 57. 58. 60. 61. 73. 127. &amp;c. But who is this <hi>Puritan?</hi> What is his name? M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Rogers</hi> in his Preface to the 39 Articles, ſaith, that ſince the ſuppreſſion of <hi>Puritans</hi> by Arch-Biſhops, <hi>Parker Grindall;</hi> and <hi>Whitegift,</hi> none will ſeeme to be ſuch irregular Profeſſors. But the eie that beholds their da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring oppoſitions in the Church, may very well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that ſuch Rebellions are taught in their <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</hi> What Rebellions? Their teaching againſt the Kings Supremacie, a reiecting of our Reformed ſaith, a refuſing of Gods holy worſhip written, which is the Common Praier-booke; a deſpiſing of Canonicall obedience; a repugning againſt our Reformed Church. Yet this ſeditious Schyſmatique would be the moſt true Reformiſt of Church, and Religion: but read the Suruey of the Pretended holy diſcipline and hence it is euidently proued, that he knowes not what he is, nor what he would be. Therefore for his
<pb facs="tcp:21422:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> better edifying, let him learne to beleeue, to pray, and obey according to the vnderſtanding Rules of this Reformed Church. For the 39 Articles are true pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of faith; all Collected out of holy writ. The Common praiers are godly praiers. The Canons are true, &amp; wholeſome lawes. Therefore he, that will not beleeue, pray and obey according to this eſtabliſhed eſtate of Church gouernment, <hi>is noe pure man in heart.</hi> He ſtudies Conſuſion of Church, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. The ſpecificall kinds of <hi>this Puritan</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe neither truth, nor goodnes: and therefore let noe man fauour their vnrighteous dealing; and let our Church ſtand faſt in her faith, inſtruct, correct, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke: that this Non-conformiſt may be a true Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt.</p>
            <p>The ſpecies; ſpecificall kinds of this <hi>Puritan</hi> are theſe. 1. <hi>the Perfectiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>the factious Sermonist.</hi> 3 <hi>the Separatiſt.</hi> 4. <hi>the Anabaptist.</hi> 5. <hi>the Brownist.</hi> 6. <hi>Loues<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>familiſt.</hi> 7. <hi>the Preciſian.</hi> 8. <hi>the Sabbatarian.</hi> 9: <hi>the Ante-diſciplinarian.</hi> 10. <hi>the Preſuming Predestina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist.</hi> Theſe ten kinds <hi>in their opinions</hi> are the beſt Chriſtians: and every one differs <hi>in the Reciprocall Quatenus</hi> (i. e.) in his proper eſſentiall Quality from other, as much as white, and blacke: yet the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of inheſion (man) may be all theſe ten, as the ſame eie is white, and blacke: though whitenes, and black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes differ eſſentially.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The <hi>Perfectist</hi> is he whoſe purenes is <hi>continuata perſeverandi actio ſanctificans;</hi> neuer to ſinne after baptiſme. This is the Nouatian Cathariſt. But
<pb facs="tcp:21422:7"/> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul did ſinne after baptiſme. Rom.</hi> 7. This is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect keeper of Gods law. Thus he is a Papiſt. But S. <hi>Paul could not doe the good, which he would, but the evill which he would not.</hi> His opinion is, that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſinning after baptiſme is damned. Our Reformed faith is; That by the grace of God, he may Repent, and amend: and thus S. <hi>Iohn; if we confeſse our ſinnes, he will forgiue.</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1. This <hi>Puritan</hi> ſinnes againſt the 16. Article.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The <hi>factious Sermoniſt,</hi> is he, whoſe purenes is, to ſerue God with ſermons, and extemporary praiers made according to his ſuppoſititious inſpiration. His opinion is vaine glory: Preachers Compos'de not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his haſty rule, he ſayth are vn-worthy, and therefore they muſt not be heard to preach, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted to, at holy Communion. Then <hi>S. Peter,</hi> (if vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthines might depoſe Preachers) ſhould neuer haue preach'd <hi>after his forſwearing his maſter.</hi> Our reformed faith is, that we may vſe the miniſtery of <hi>vnworthy Miniſters.</hi> And tis ſtrange that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends himſelfe to be worthy: whereas <hi>S. Paul</hi> is not a teacher of his opinion. 2. Cor. 2. 16. in theſe words. <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> This ſinneth againſt the 26. Article. Another opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his, is that <hi>preaching is better than Praier.</hi> But both being moſt neceſſarie: Preaching for to inſtruct the people; and praier to worſhip God, inſtrumentally to cauſe regeneration by baptiſme &amp;c. It followes, that this <hi>Sermoniſt</hi> is a peeuiſh diſturber of Religion. A third opinion of his, is, that <hi>priuate Praier</hi> made by a tardy commer to
<pb facs="tcp:21422:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> Church is <hi>the ſacrifice of fools.</hi> As if too late co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to Church were not a ſinne to be repented of: and that one ſoe ill prepar'd to ioyne with the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, ſhould not pray for remiſſion, and Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and then praiſe the Lord with the whole Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The <hi>Separatiſt</hi> is he, whoſe Purenes is Phariſaicall. He commends himſelfe in the Temple to be farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all others for holines: Our Sauiour ſayth that the <hi>Publican repenting was more iuſt than he. Luke</hi> 18. 14. His opinion is, <hi>that only he is the Elect, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, and faithfull child of God.</hi> And that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are reprobates, the wicked, the vnregenerat, and the damned: <hi>But Gods iudgments are vnſearchable. Rom.</hi> 11. 33. <hi>And who art thou that iudgeſt? why doſt thou Iudge &amp;c? Rom.</hi> 14. 4. 10. 11. 12. 13. The iudgment of our Church is, that al that are baptized are regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat: Thus, <hi>Seeing that this child is regenerat &amp; graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the body of Chriſts congregation &amp;c.</hi> And the Church regulated by ſcriptures <hi>is the pillar and grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of truth.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15. therefore belieue our Church. Regeneration is by infuſion of grace, by ſowing the good ſeed: (it differs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> increaſe of grace, &amp; perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is <hi>ortus boniſeminis,</hi> the ſpringing of good ſeed: <hi>This good ſeed did grow in ſtony and thorny ground.</hi> Regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the individual act, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Chriſtians. Increaſe of grace &amp; perſevera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue Chriſtians. And morall perſwaſion cannot rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate ſtony and thorny hearts dead in ſinne. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore regeneration being the individuall act of God
<pb facs="tcp:21422:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> bound to his Church by his owne covenant, iudge as our Church doth, concerning the baptized; that all baptized are regenerate. The grace of Gods covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth admit of noe <hi>Separatiſts:</hi> for it did not ſeparate, but bind <hi>Iſaac</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſmael</hi> vnto God in obedience: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth it ſeparate, but vnite the baptized vnto Chriſt. As for the ſeparating iudgement according to the mercifull decree of election who are the ſaved: this belongs only to God to pronounce. But let all Chriſtians religiouſly pray and liue according to the grace of reſtitution, and humbly ſubmit their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, concerning the ſecrecy of perſonall election. The <hi>Separatiſt</hi> ſinnes againſt the 17. Article, which ſayth that <hi>Gods election is ſecret to vs, for we know not the elect by their particular names.</hi> He ſinnes againſt the 35 article at the 2. 4. 5. 6. 7. 10. 11. 15. 19. 20. 21. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie. For theſe doe charitably exhort the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation to obey and honour God; whereas the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſt is noe freind of Publicans and ſinners: but the vncharitable accuſer of our Saviours pittied co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The <hi>Anabaptist</hi> is he, whoſe purenes is a ſuppoſed birth without originall ſinne. And yet our bodies are parts of <hi>Adams</hi> nature, that did ſinne. And no man was borne without ſinne, <hi>Chriſt only excepted.</hi> His te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net is, that infants muſt not be baptized. <hi>Yet Iſaac was circumciſed the eighth day.</hi> And to be <hi>circumei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> and <hi>baptized</hi> are one, and the ſame in effect. And <hi>Abrahams</hi> Religion, and ours are the ſame. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 9. 14. 15. 16. 17. And therefore by a neceſſarie ſeale of the Covenant, we muſt doe, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did; <hi>binde little</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21422:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>children in covenant to God.</hi> This <hi>Puritan</hi> ſinnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the 9 &amp; 27 Articles. The one affirmeth <hi>that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are borne in originall ſin;</hi> the other, <hi>that infants must be baptized.</hi> If infants be borne without origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne: then tis noe controverſy; That originall ſin foreſeene is not the meritorious cauſe of reprobation. The ſinner deſerues, &amp; the iudg intends puniſhment. So 'tis certaine, that ſinne is not the foreſeene inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding efficient of that preordain'd puniſhing decree. And it is without queſtion, that Gods Supremacy may pardon or puniſh <hi>pro abſoluto beneplacito,</hi> only as he will, ſeeing 'tis the prerogatiue of ſupremacy, he being ſupreame Iudg. But he <hi>cannot be iuſt in decree,</hi> if he ſo reprobates, but for ſinne foreſeene. For the law was not, that any ſhould die in <hi>Adam,</hi> if <hi>he</hi> had not eaten of the forbidden fruit: <hi>and therfore this law in previſion tranſgreſſed is the meritorious efficient of reprobation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The <hi>Browniſt</hi> is he, whoſe purenes is to ſerue God in woods and feilds. He is a wildernes of pureneſſe. His opinion is, that Idolatry cannot be reformed without pulling downe of Churches. But King <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> commaunded <hi>the Levites to ſanctifie the houſe of the Lord, and to carry forth the filthines out of the ſanctuary &amp;c.</hi> 2. Chron. 29. 5. And our Saviour <hi>whipt the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple:</hi> though it was prophan'd, yet without any pulling downe, he calls it <hi>the houſe of prayer.</hi> Mat. 21. 12. 13. This <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan</hi> ſinnes againſt the 35 Article, at the 1 homily, which teacheth a decent keeping of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <hi>Loves familiſt</hi> is he, whoſe purenes is to ſerue
<pb facs="tcp:21422:9"/> God as wel at his Neighbors charge, as at his owne. <hi>Omnia ſunt Communia:</hi> no one ſaith, that the things, which theſe Loue-Maſters poſſeſſe are their owne, but all are Common. Yet S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>that he is worſe then an Infidell that provideth not for his owne family.</hi> If he be poore, his poore purenes muſt not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with his hands to get his liuing, though he be a Mechanicke, he muſt only meditate on the word. Yet the text ſaith <hi>he that will not Labour, let him not eate.</hi> He in his conceipt is a greater S. then S. <hi>Iohn the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> and that he is in perſecution for the Goſpell; and therefore <hi>Ananias</hi> doth ſell his poſſeſſions, that the poore brother may participate of his brotherly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Concerning S. <hi>Iohn</hi> our Sauiour ſaith <hi>that he was as great a Prophet,</hi> as any borne of a woman. Concerning <hi>Ananias</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith <hi>that he diſſembled with the holy Ghoſt: Concerning this poore Saints perſequution for the Goſpell:</hi> his puniſhment is iuſtly to be inflicted on him for abuſing the goſpell with his deceipt to maintaine idlenes: His neighbour ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'de to ſel, <hi>is vndone:</hi> this is iniurie which muſt not eſcape vnpuniſhed. This <hi>Puritan</hi> ſinnes againſt the 38 Article. For this truth is to be beleeu'd, that as in perſequution, the rich did releiue the poore Saints: So in the time of peace, all able men muſt labour, to preſerue the Common wealth. Here, note, that <hi>Loues-familiſt</hi> in the 38 Article is called the <hi>Anabaptiſt:</hi> and tis true <hi>ſubiectiuè; ſed non formaliter.</hi> The ſame man may be <hi>Loues-familiſt,</hi> and the <hi>Anabaptiſt:</hi> but to be formally the <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> is not to be <hi>Loues-familiſt</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21422:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> their definitions differ.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The <hi>Preciſian</hi> is he, whoſe purenes is, not to ſweare before a Magiſtrate. yet <hi>this kind of ſwearing</hi> is commanded Deut. 6. 13. He teacheth that vnlawfull <hi>ſwearing</hi> is a greater ſinne, than murther. God indeed is greater than man, Hence is the compare, But the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect deſtructiue is greater by murther, for thereby mans life is deſtroyed, but vnlawfull ſwearing cannot wound ſo deepe. And God commands that the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer die the death, <hi>blood muſt be ſhed for blood;</hi> he deales not ſoe ſeuerely with the ſwearer. This <hi>Puritan</hi> ſinnes againſt the 39. Article: which teacheth that tis lawfull to ſweare before a magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The <hi>Sabbatarian</hi> is he, whoſe purenes is to preach downe all holy dayes. Preaching; the inſtrumentall directing cauſe to keepe holy the ſabbath day, he makes to be the keeping holy the Sabbath; but Gods holy worſhip, common praier is this keeping holy the ſabbath day. For preaching the holy direction teacheth holy worſhip common praiers to be the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſe of that day to praiſe the Lord for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption &amp;c. This is the ſole principall end of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching on the Lords day. The Sabbatarians preaching is a Sylua ſynonymorum, Tantologies, Iterations. His praying is too much brainſike babling. His opinion is; <hi>Labour thou ſixe dayes: therefore there must be noe holy dayes,</hi> but the Lords day. Tis true in an vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding iudicious ſence: Thus. Thou muſt praiſe God for the Creation, Redemption, Reſtitution, and preſeruation of the world: To praiſe God for theſe
<pb facs="tcp:21422:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> cauſes, <hi>onely the</hi> 7. <hi>day is ſet</hi> apart: which is not the <hi>Iewes</hi> Sabbath, the ſabbath only for the creation. But this is the day following: when Chriſt reſted from ſubduing ſinne, hell, and death: when the <hi>Lord Ieſus ceaſed from his worke. Heb.</hi> 4. He then <hi>appoynted a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine day, by ſaying to day ver.</hi> 7. And becauſe Chriſt reſted from his worke of reſtoring his kingdome to Iſrael in the ſame manner, as God did from his, ver. 10. appointing the firſt day after the creation to be the ſabbath. Therefore the firſt day of the Iewes weeke, the ſcripture calls, and tis inſtituted for to be the Lords day; <hi>for this is the day of Chriſts reſt religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to be celebrated with holy worſhip in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our iustifying, ſanctifying, ſauing, victorious, and trivmphing Redemption.</hi> But concerning other holy dayes <hi>there were ſeauen together, in the time of the law.</hi> Deut. 16. Therefore when God was to be praiſed for preſeruing Iſrael in tents, when he brought them out of Aegipt &amp;c: then the text ſaith not, <hi>labor</hi> 6. <hi>dayes, but keepe holy</hi> 7. <hi>dayes</hi> &amp;c. So when God is to be <hi>praiſed for the Angells good newes to the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin, for the Natiuity of our Sauiour, for his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion &amp;c:</hi> then the Church teacheth not 6. dayes labour, but to praiſe the Lord on the holy time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted. This <hi>Puritan</hi> ſinnes againſt the 35. Article at the 7. 12. 13. 14. 16. and 17 homilies. For theſe doe teach the holy obſeruing of feaſts vnto the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> The <hi>Anti-diſciplinarian</hi> is he, whoſe purenes is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Kings Supremacy. Imperious Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! His holines is the Churches greateſt Authority,
<pb facs="tcp:21422:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> and as good a Rule for to know the Reformed true faith, as holy writ. He is a ſtrict obſeruer of the law, therefore his Religion is the beſt religion. But our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour teacheth, that <hi>mercy is the best part of Religion.</hi> Matth. 9. 13. And he neuer learned, <hi>that Christs kings office is aboue Christs Prieſts office, in ſpirituall things:</hi> for as much as Chriſt a Prieſt, died for to make ſatisfaction for our ſins, to God the Supreame Iudge, who is Chriſt a king: and that from this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt a king, the king is derived: and that the Prieſt is derived from Chriſts Prieſts office. This <hi>Puritans</hi> tenet is, <hi>that kings muſt be ſubiect to the Puritan-Presbyters Cenſure, ſubmit their Scepters, throw downe their Crownes, and licke vp the duſt of their feete.</hi> Thus <hi>Mr</hi> 
               <hi>Rogers</hi> in the 11. page of his Preface to the 39. Articles: and thus <hi>T. C. teacheth in his Reply,</hi> page 180. Thus the oath of Supremacie, &amp; allegiance are broken. This <hi>Puritan</hi> is an Arch-trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. His prowd holyneſſe ſinnes againſt the 21. Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which affirmeth, that <hi>Princes in their Dominions haue ſupreame Authority to gather together Generall Councels,</hi> and againſt the 35. Article at the laſt homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which <hi>preacheth downe Rebellion:</hi> and againſt the 37. Article, which ſaith, that <hi>the King is ſupreame Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of Church and Common Wealth next, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately vnder Christ in his Dominions; in all cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and over all Perſons Eccleſiasticall, and Civill.</hi> His tenet is, that all Prieſts ſhould be Equall. But who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gaue all Prieſts authority to ordaine, and did exalt inferiour Prieſts, and pull downe Superiors for that equality; but <hi>Farellus,</hi> and <hi>Viretus</hi> (by Sermons) two
<pb facs="tcp:21422:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Geneva-Presbyters.</hi> But by what Law? Whence was that authority? This <hi>Puritan</hi> ſinnes againſt the 23, 33 and 36. Articles, which teach the lawfulnes of <hi>Arch-Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops Superiority,</hi> and <hi>Iuriſdiction.</hi> This <hi>Puritan</hi> is an enemie to Church-Ceremonies, as if Gods Miniſters, and his houſe ſhould be <hi>naked,</hi> without all externall beauty. He ſaith, that he is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for <hi>eſsentials</hi> at baptizing, &amp;c. And yet Metaphyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call divinitie is farre beyond the ſpheare of his <hi>plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and briefly, &amp;c.</hi> For the Scriptures deduceable ſence tranſcends his capacitie. This <hi>Puritan</hi> ſinnes againſt the 20. Article.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> The <hi>Preſuming Predeſtinatiſt</hi> is he, whoſe purenes is an inſpired knowledge, that hee ſhalbe ſaved by Gods abſolute election. He is ſo ſure of his ſalvation, as if he were now in heaven: as if thete were no life in him, <hi>but Gods eſsentiall glory.</hi> This is to ſin without feare or wit. He conſidereth not, that the World, the fleſh, and the Deuill are ſuch cruell, and ſubtile enemies, that they did ſoe terrifie <hi>S. Peter</hi> as that he denied, with an oath, that he knew <hi>the Rocke of Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and the other <hi>Apoſtles</hi> fled. And pray thou Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, that thou enter not into temptation. Thus the 17. Article teacheth thee. And preſume not that thou art abſolutely certaine of ſaluation, for <hi>in denying Chriſts ſoules locall deſcent</hi> into Hell, which is againſt the 3 Article, thou denieſt a part of <hi>Chriſts ſubduing euill ſpirits,</hi> and <hi>his triumph ouer the power of hell:</hi> for this end <hi>Chriſt deſcended to the ſpirits, that were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient in the daies of Noah.</hi> 1. Pet. 3. 18. 19. 20. And
<pb facs="tcp:21422:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> thou ſeemeſt to deny <hi>that good workes are the stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving inſtrumentall cauſes for ſalvation,</hi> in that thou regardeſt not Examples of good life, by abhorring <hi>Apocrypha ſcripture,</hi> which is againſt the 6. Article. Suffer the words of exhortation: be not factious in the Church, <hi>to mainetaine an Imperious ruinating holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to amaze ſilly people, to gaine a competency, by way of collection.</hi> God hath given <hi>the tenth part in al Iſraell for an inheritance,</hi> to mainetaine the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hood. <hi>Num.</hi> 18. 21. And if the humane poſitiue law hath not made proviſion according to this divine law, ſtay the Lords leaſure, till he ſhall aſſiſt the king, and the generall Councell of this land, to reforme this thing, as yet full of difficultie. If thou haſt no Benefice; faction can never bring thee any <hi>de iure;</hi> but reformation may. Downe on thy knees; repent, and amend: and praiſe God Almighty, for as much as thy Dread Soveraigne Lord, and king, hath ſpared thy life ſo long; thou being nothing better <hi>in tenet, than an Arch-Traitor.</hi> Downe on thy knees &amp; giue harty thankes to God; in that the Moſt Reverend Arch-Biſhops, and the Right Reverend Biſhops, thy holy and Ghoſtly Fathers, haue not delivered thee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to Satan, <hi>Maiori Excommunicatione,</hi> curſing thee forth, from the Church, and all humane ſocietie, thou being a moſt <hi>contumacious Schyſmatique.</hi> It is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, that thou deny, that thou art any ſuch <hi>Puritan;</hi> for thy faction is viſible (almoſt) every where in this land. Downe on thy knees, and pray for Gods holy ſpirits illumination; that thy zeale may be according
<pb facs="tcp:21422:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> to the infallible knowing faith, and that God may thus incline thy heart to our <hi>true, faithfull, reforming Chriſtian Religion.</hi> The Lord Almighty, and moſt mercifull, make the light of his countenance to ſhine vpon thee, and to reforme thee. Then the Church ſhal enioy her much deſired vnitie: In which how happy a thing it is for Brethren to dwell together, for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to liue, and die; I deſire you, to conſider; I pray you; I beſeech you: Even I, though I am very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainefully hated of you, am ſo charitably affected: &amp; I labour alwaies to the vtmoſt of my praiers, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, to inſtruct you with true ſanctifying reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo ſhall till death remaine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your hearty well-wiſher to ſolid Reformation, <hi>GILES WIDDOWES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21422:12"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1. COR. 14. V. VLT.</bibl>
               <q>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE 19. of the 39. Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Religion af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes, that <hi>the Church may erre, that the Church hath erred.</hi> The reaſon, why the erring Church is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the loſt ſheep, is <hi>becauſe ſhee ſubmits not vnto the onely true rule of faith, which is Gods faithfull word.</hi> The 20. Article ſaith, <hi>that the church cannot erre:</hi> that tis no erring church, but a true church, not a church voide of authority, but a church having authority, <hi>to decree Rites, and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, to handle, iudge, and decide the hard, ſubtile, and deceiving controverſies of faith.</hi> For this well tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and well governed church obſerues Gods not deceaving, nor deceaved word to be her <hi>principium fidei, her principle of faith to be faithfully beleeved: to</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21422:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>be her true ſignifying Rule, to be taught, learned, and kept.</hi> Whatſoeuer is contrary to this heavenly voice, ſhe hates being all diabolicall lies: whatſoever expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition doth make ſcripture to be contrary to ſcripture ſhe examines, confutes, &amp; reformes by the true rules of expoſition. Whatſoever is beſides ſcripture ſhee reiects for mans inveution, for humane tradition, for ſuperfluous, vnneceſſarie. <hi>Herein the church is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full keeper, and a faithfull witneſſe of holy writ.</hi> And let the church; let this church perſevere a faithfull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and a faithfull keeper of Gods moſt true, and moſt holy word, <hi>to preſerue her authority in rites, and ceremonies, in reſolving Faiths factious controverſies; to expound the ſcripture learnedly according to rule</hi> in ſummo gradu neceſſitatis, <hi>in the propriety of truth;</hi> and to reiect mans flattering additions prudently, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods all-ſufficient precept. This is the ſumme of <hi>S. Pauls</hi> ſpirituall councell to adviſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the church.</p>
            <q>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</q>
            <p>Which words are the ſubſtance of the 20. of the 39. Articles of religion; &amp; they containe fowre parts. The firſt is <hi>Commande Authorizing: Let.</hi> The ſecond is, <hi>how many things are Authorized: All things.</hi> The third is, <hi>the obeying of this commaunding Authority. Be done.</hi> The fourth is, <hi>the manner of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying this command.</hi> This is, <hi>Decently, and in order.</hi> In the <hi>commande Authorizing</hi> obſerue Who, and what Commands: who commands? This is firſt God the Holy Ghoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſecondly <hi>S. Paul.</hi> What commands?
<pb facs="tcp:21422:13"/> This is Gods will; this is Gods word. <hi>Let.</hi> In how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things there are authorized, obſerue the doctrine of faith, the diſcipline, the rites, and ceremonies of the church. <hi>All things.</hi> In the obeying of this commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Authority: obſerue who muſt obey: and this is the church. Secondly, that ſhee doth obey: in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the doctrine, diſcipline, rites, and ceremonies commaunded. <hi>Be done. Let all things be done.</hi> In the manner of obeying this commaund obſerue how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-fold this manner is; and this is twofold: firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently: ſecondly in order: in the outſide by beawtie, decently; within, and without according to rule: <hi>In order. Let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi> You haue the diuiſion of my text: God commaunding the Church <hi>to decencie, and order of doctrine, and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline:</hi> and therefore let no man accuſe me ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that I am not come to edifie: for if Gods, S. <hi>Paules</hi> doctrine, and diſcipline may edifie, I ſhall edifie. And let noe temporizing faction act <hi>the diſſembling Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite,</hi> and ſay, that my doctrine is not true, but ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: for I am come to you with the doctrine of our receaued, and eſtabliſhed faith. And let no trembling <hi>Neuter</hi> plead that my words are too deepe myſteries to be vnderſtood. No: but let him ſtriue to know his Faith, how it differs from hereſie, that he may be true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faithfull in the pure, and vndefiled Religion. My text doth not ſtay to requeſt, but requires: my text doth not intreate, and pray, but doth will, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund you to be faithfully religious: and that in a word, and that in the firſt word of my text.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21422:14"/>
            <q>Let.</q>
            <p>This word is commaund: though tis but a ſigne, yet by it commaund is vnderſtood, and vnderſtood to ſpeake: not by prohibition, to make any ſtopp, or ſtay: but with commaund to make haſt, and not to fayle at your perill. This <hi>Let</hi> is the actiue part of Gods commaund in the firſt place of S. Paule in the ſecond place, in perſon commaunding, thirdly of the ſcripture, which is S. Paules commaund, which is Gods ſouereigne and vncontrouleable commaund. You know the almighty power of Gods commaund; that by it he made nothing to be all things. For he ſpake, and it was done, he commaunded, and it ſtood faſt. And ſhall he now ſpeake, and ſhall nothing be done? Shall he now commaund, and ſhall nothing ſtand faſt? Gods word is ſharper then any two edged ſword: and 'tis as poſſible to reſiſt Gods word, and liue eternally, as 'tis to reſiſt a ſword dividing the heart and after that, to enioy this temporall life. At the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the law, Gods voyce was ſo terrible, <hi>that the people, that heard, intreated that the word ſhould not be ſpoken to them any more for feare of death. Heb.</hi> 12. 19. For Gods voyce did then ſhake the earth, <hi>and it ſhall once more ſhake both heaven and earth. Heb.</hi> 12. 26. Here is maieſtie, and power: and Gods will muſt be done, for he commaunds, to the terrifying of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and earth. Gods word is not a bare ſound, but his word is a conuerting word: and if the conuerted will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:21422:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> not ſtand in grace, God hauing giuen the will, and the deede, what doe they that reſiſt, but neglect great ſaluation? <hi>But ſee, that yee refuſe not him, that ſpeaketh: For if they eſcaped not, who refuſed him, that ſpake on earth, much more ſhall not we eſcape, if we turne away from him, that ſpeaketh from heauen. Heb.</hi> 12. 25. It concernes you then very much, to heare Gods commaund: <hi>S. Paule,</hi> Gods deputed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder, tells you that it concernes your ſaluation: and looſe this looſe all the world. But whats the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that mens hearts are ſo litle knowne to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding God. Who hath bewitched them, that they will not obey truth? T'is true, that there muſt be <hi>Hereſies:</hi> for lying and diſſembling tongues doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, ſeduce, and vnder a colour of a little godlines, bring Church, and Common wealth into confuſion, and deſtruction of ſoule and body. And is it not then high time to exhort you with <hi>S. Paule, Beware of dogs; beware of evill workers Philip.</hi> 3. 2. Beware of them, that barke at the Articles of religion. Beware of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that bite at the gouernment of the Church. Beware of fiery zeale ſet on fire by a factious ſpirit. Beware of deſpiſers of Gouernours, of inuentors of evill things. Beware of the diſobedient. For they hate the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and diſcipline; the rites, and ceremonies of the Church, which is my ſecond part of text, implyed in theſe words.</p>
            <q>All Things.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>By all things,</hi> are not vnderſtood all things of this world: for they are enmitie againſt God. But by <hi>All</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21422:15"/> 
               <hi>thinges,</hi> are vnderſtood all things, which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to build, and beautifie the Church, which God commands to gouerne, &amp; preſerue the Church. So that theſe <hi>All things</hi> are all Eccleſiaſticall things: all things, that belong to the Church. The text doth mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>prophecying, ſpeaking with tongues, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>faith, hope, and charitie.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13: <hi>all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall guifts.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12: <hi>the Ceremonies of the Church.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11: <hi>the ſacraments; Baptiſme, The Lords ſupper:</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10: <hi>the Miniſters dues</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9: <hi>Meats offer'd to idolls not to be eaten</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. <hi>Marriage, and ſingle life.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <hi>Forbearing to goe to law one with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>Excommunication</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>reuerence due to the Cleargie.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4: <hi>diuiſion, and ſectes in the Church. Chap.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Doctrina generalis hic tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur circa Doctrinam, &amp; precepta diuina? leges de deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, &amp; ordine Eccleſiae, circa ritus, &amp; circa externam diſciplinam: ſo Pareus. By all things</hi> are vnderſtood the doctrine of the Church; divine precepts; lawes for decencie, and order of the Church; the Churches rites, and externall diſcipline. The doctrine of the Church is here vnderſtood. The doctrine of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, which is the law, and the Goſpell, the old, and the new Teſtament, and here is vnderſtood the doctrine of the Reformed Church, which is the 39. Articles of Religion. This is the materiall breife of all Chriſtian doctrine, and let this ſuffice for this preſent. For to ſpeake particularly to every part of faith in the old, and new Teſtament, and in the 39. Articles of Religion, is more then the tongue of men,
<pb facs="tcp:21422:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> and Angells is able to deliuer within the ſhort limits of an howre. The diſcipline of the Church is here vnderſtood, which is the ordayning of Superiours and their gouerning: and 'tis the practiſe, and humble obedience of inferiours. This is <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and all inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Magiſtrates iudging, and gouerning. This is <hi>Aarons,</hi> and all inferiour Preiſts expounding, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing the people: and 'tis the Magiſtrates, Preiſts, and peoples reverent worſhipping the Lord, and their ſincere keeping of the law. The Imperiall, and Preiſtlie gouerment ſtill remaine, not in rigour, for that our Sauiour hath mitigated: but they are ſtill Authorities: one ſupremely commanding, the other is ſupremely inſtructing. Kings are nurſing fathers, and Queenes are nurſing Mothers: and they are ſo much higher than Preiſts, as Chriſts Kings office in ſpirituall things is higher than Chriſts Preiſts office in ſpirituall things. The ſuperioritie ſtill ſtands a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie in the Clergie. There was a ſuperioritie ſtill in the Miniſterie. Chriſt aboue the twelue Apoſtles, the twelue Apoſtles aboue the ſeuentie diſciples: S. <hi>Paule</hi> aboue <hi>Timothie, Timothy</hi> aboue the <hi>Preſbyters</hi> in the Church of <hi>Epheſus in doctrine, and manners of the Church.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1: <hi>in ordaining Biſhopps, &amp; Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3: <hi>in having authoritie to puniſh the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders offending, and other Church-offenders.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim. Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 6. At the 326. yeare after Chriſt, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Nice</hi> decreed, that there ſhould be in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church three Patriarchs; one at <hi>Rome,</hi> one at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> one at <hi>Antioch</hi> to gouerne inferiour
<pb facs="tcp:21422:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> Biſhops. Religion was planted in this land by S. <hi>Paule,</hi> So <hi>Parſons</hi> the Ieſuite: and by <hi>Simon Zelotes,</hi> So M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Maſon</hi> out of <hi>Necephorus,</hi> and <hi>Dorotheus:</hi> and by <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> Biſhop of Britaine, ſo <hi>Dorotheus:</hi> and by <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> ſo <hi>Iohn Capgraue:</hi> and that in the life of <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi> ſo <hi>Gildas:</hi> in the 35 yeare of Chriſt, ſo learned B. <hi>Morton</hi> cap. 3. ſect. 9. of the Grand Impoſture hath obſerued out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Papiſts, Cardinall <hi>Baronius,</hi> and the Ieſuite <hi>Suarez.</hi> From the yeare of the Lord 179. there were Arch-biſhops &amp; Biſhops in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> ſo <hi>Lelandus:</hi> and they haue ſucceſſiuely continued to this day. In their firſt conſecration till 600 years after Chriſt they were Primitiue Biſhops: From 600 years till 1533 they were Popiſh, corrupt, ſicke with hereſy almoſt to the death. From 1533 they haue 5 years excepted, continued good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe reformed Biſhops. Here note that our Church did not beginne a little after <hi>Luther,</hi> but being ſicke with Popery, ſhe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recouered her Apoſtolicall faith. Like as a ſick man recouering, then enters not into the World to beginne his life, but into the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of his former health: ſo Popery and Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme being purged out of theſe parts of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, 'twas not then a new planted: but a new reformed Church. <hi>All things.</hi> Here is vnderſtood Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline. The King doth gouerne by Chriſts regall power and command. The Biſhop doth gouerne by the key of knowledge and by the key of iuriſdiction. The Biſhop doth gouerne in the
<pb facs="tcp:21422:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> Church by the key of knowledge in that he giues au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority by ordaination &amp; miſſion to able and fit men for to preach, to pray, &amp;c. in the Church. By the key of iuriſdiction the Biſhop doth gouerne in the Conſiſtory by examining and cenſuring with the helpe of his Iudge-aſſiſtant. To know all Church-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, I referre you to the Rubricke in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-praier-booke, to the Canons of the Church, &amp;c. This part of my text is <hi>All things,</hi> and therefore I muſt not omit the rites, &amp; ceremonies of the Church: for they are vnderſtood in theſe <hi>All things.</hi> The rites, and ceremonies of the Church, which were tipicall in the <hi>Iewes</hi> time, did ſignifie Chriſt to come: and therefore at Chriſts comming they were abrogated. <hi>Quia veritas venit, ſignum tollitur:</hi> ſo <hi>S. Auguſtine.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt is come into the fleſh there is no vſe of a ſigne, to ſignifie, that Chriſt is to come. But in our church the ceremonies are <hi>not typicall; but they are ſignes of church-beauty for morall ornament.</hi> And that to beautify geſture in acknowledging the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> to be King of heauen and earth, of the triumphant &amp; militant Church; hence it is, that in Church-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies we bow at the name of <hi>Ieſus:</hi> or to beautify ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture at praier, when we pray, <hi>The body and blood of our Lord Ieſus Christ preſerue ſoule and body to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting life,</hi> &amp;c. hence it is, that we humbly, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently kneele on our knees at receiuing the Lords ſupper. Or in token, that we will not be aſhamed <hi>to confes the faith of Christ crucified, &amp; manfully to fight vnder his banner, &amp;c.</hi> hence it is that little Children
<pb facs="tcp:21422:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> baptized after the forme of baptiſme are ſigned with the ſigne of the croſſe: or to ſignify the ſincerity of the Miniſters vnſpotted faith: hence it is that our Church-prieſts doe weare the ſurpleſſe, at performing holy worſhip to God: or to ſignify the vndeuided loue of husband and wife, till death them depart: hence it is, that in marriage the ring is giuen for a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and pledge: or to ſignify a thankfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance vnto God, for giueing vs Chriſtian examples, and encouragements, to perſeuere in the true Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall faith: in that God gaue vs his Sonne, his one, and only Sonne to be our Mediatour; and the Bleſſed Virgin to bee his Mother; according to his humanity, the holy Apoſtles to preach Chriſt Ieſus, the Saviour, to the ends of the world; for giving vs many and miraculous deliverances from great, and apparent dangers; hence it is that Holy-dayes were ordain'd, and are kept: <hi>The nativitie of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: The purification of the Bleſsed Virgin, &amp;c.</hi> to praiſe the Lord. And herein we tranſgreſſe not the fourth commandement. <hi>Sixe daies ſhalt thou labour, &amp;c.</hi> For that law bindes vs to thanke the Lord for the creation, and Reſtitution of the World<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and God requires but the ſeuenth day to performe our holy thankſgiuings vnto him in the publique congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and yet he requires other holy daies vpon other ſpeciall reaſons, as 'tis proued hereafter at <hi>Leuiticus</hi> 23. Church pictures are an <hi>externall beauty of the Church, a memory of honour to the dead;</hi> and S. <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> cals them lay mens bookes. <hi>Church. Organs are mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21422:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>ſignes of our exultation:</hi> they are the lowd, and as ſweet as lowd, expreſſions of the Churches grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ioy towards God: ſo are church-Bells, though ſometimes they are the churches ſolemne call, that Gods people ſhould aſſemble to worſhip the Lord with holy worſhip. And ſeeing that I haue procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thus farre in the Narration of church-rites, and ceremonies, giue me leaue to tell you, how ancient Godfathers, and Godmothers haue beene in the church: and how long interrogatories haue beene vſed at baptizing little children. They are as ancient as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Areopagite, as it appeareth in his ſeaventh chapter <hi>de Eccleſiaſtica Hierarchia,</hi> who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the 70. yeare after Chriſt. The church is not <hi>Abrahams</hi> private houſe, when he was witneſſe to his ſonne <hi>Iſaacs</hi> circumciſing: but the church is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, and therefore ſhee muſt accordingly haue witneſſes to preſerue her catholique communion of faith. Tis a ceremonie, a rite of the church, to bring the dead body, the corps into the body of the church. For that body Chriſt did ſanctifie with his blood, and did make it the temple of the holy Ghoſt: And therefore at performing of our laſt duety, wee muſt not thruſt it out at church-dores; but honour it with church-entertainement. For bleſſed are the dead, for whom the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> laid downe his life. I haue giuen you a view of <hi>All things,</hi> of <hi>All things</hi> in my text. 'Tis Church doctrine let your faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it. 'Tis Church diſcipline, let your liues obſerue and Keepe it. 'Tis Church ceremonie, let your fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
<pb facs="tcp:21422:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> vſe exerciſe and renew it. In the firſt place you ſhall honour God your Almighty Father. In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place you ſhall honour the vnity of brethren: which the Pſalmiſt commends with admiration: <hi>Oh how good and ioyfull a thing it is, brethren to dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in vnity.</hi> God hath not authorized theſe things, that you ſhould neglect them, but his good pleaſure is that they ſhould <hi>Be Done. Let all things be done,</hi> which is my third part of text, and followes next to be handled in theſe words,</p>
            <q>Be Done.</q>
            <p>This is the obeying of a commanding authority, 'Tis the Church that obeys: For ſhe obſerues, and keepes <hi>the doctrine, the diſcipline, the rites and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Church.</hi> The ſcripture is the command: <hi>Let all things be done:</hi> and the Church obeys. And then compare, which is the greater in authority, <hi>ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that which commands,</hi> or that which obeyes? To obey is vnder authority, command, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scripture is greater in authority then the Church. The Churches obedience is not only paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue, ſtill to be an hearer only: but the Churches o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is alſo actiue, for ſhe muſt not be only an hearer of the Scripture, of the law: but ſhe muſt be a doer alſo. Firſt ſhee muſt heare the Scripture ſay, <hi>Let all things be done;</hi> and then ſhee muſt doe, what ſhe heares commanded to be done. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Fiant, inquit à vobis, &amp; vestro conſilio.</hi> So <hi>Pareus:</hi> when the Scripture hath ſaid it, <hi>Then let all things be done by the Church, &amp; by the iudgement of the church.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21422:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> Here the Apoſtle hath <hi>by Scripture given authority to the Church</hi> to gouerne decently, and in order, in doctrine, in divine precepts, in Church-diſcipline. And therefore the Church may in the firſt place ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound according to rules of expoſition, and make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lawes which ſhe ſees to be decent, and orderly in every place. <hi>Omnes Eccleſiarum, Epiſcoporum, Docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum leges &amp;c. de decoro, &amp; ordine externo, &amp;c. diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere debent. Pareus.</hi> The lawes of Churches, of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, of Doctors, muſt beautifie, and order the Church. <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi> Theſe words doe authorize the Church to ordaine Church-orders, expoſitions, rites, and ceremonies, &amp; that not of late, but from the Apoſtles times: ſo <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin Martyr, Irenaeus, Tertullian,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Cyprian,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Baſill,</hi> S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and fiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells ſay the ſame. But what doth the Scripture ſay, that there muſt be any ſuch traditions? Yes the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith the ſame. Read 1. Cor. 11. 2. &amp; 1. Cor. 11. 34. And Church-ceremonies are contain'd in the ſcriptures, not in expreſſe ſentence, but by pregnant conſequence, by vertue whereof the Apoſtle doth grant a generall licenſe, &amp; authority to all Churches, to ordaine any ceremonies, that may bee fit for the better ſerving of God: ſo our Right reverend and learned Biſhop <hi>Morton.</hi> The ſame ceremonies will not ſort in all places, and therefore our Saviour left them to the different diſpoſition, &amp; cuſtome of times, and countries: ſo <hi>Calvin</hi> lib. 4. Inſtitut. cap. 10. parag. 30. Therefore to deny this power to the Church, to
<pb facs="tcp:21422:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> ordaine ceremonies, is to depriue her of chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: ſo <hi>Bucer.</hi> If our Church-ceremonies were dumbe, non-ſignificant, they might bee well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd for vnlawfull, but they being ſignificant, are lawfull: ſo <hi>Kemnitius:</hi> being ſignificant, they are profitable for admonition, and teſtification of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. ſo B. <hi>Iewell, Kemnitius,</hi> and <hi>Zanchius.</hi> The cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of our church haue ſpeciall ſignification: they are ſignes, and doe ſignifie, not with ſacramentall ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, but with decently morall. For they are ſignes of Church-beauty for moral ornament, as you haue heard by the bowing <hi>at the name of Ieſus,</hi> &amp; by other Church-ceremonies in my former particular. Our Church-ceremonies, our Church-traditions are grounded on good authority; for they are contain'd in the Scriptures; <hi>in genere ent is, aut in virtute cauſae, either in their generall, or in the power of their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall cauſe.</hi> My Text will ſerue for the generall to ſignifie all Church-ceremonies; and my Text ſerues for the cauſe, to ordaine all Church-traditions that are lawfull. <hi>All things decently, and in order;</hi> there are all Church-ceremonies ſignified. <hi>Let them be done:</hi> there is Church authority giuen by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to cauſe them to be ordain'd. But to bow <hi>at the name of Ieſus,</hi> this is expreſſe Scripture, Philip. 2. 10. To kneele <hi>at prayer,</hi> this is expreſſe Scripture, Pſalm. 95. 6. and wee pray at receiuing the Lords Supper. <hi>The body of our Lord Ieſus Christ, preſerue my ſoule and body to everlaſting life. To take vp the Croſſe and follow Chriſt,</hi> is expreſſe Scripture, Mat. 16. 24. And
<pb facs="tcp:21422:19"/> to take vp the Croſſe is the fundamentall cauſe of the ſigne of the Croſſe to bee done decently &amp; in order. <hi>The man and wife are one fleſh,</hi> is expreſſe Scripture. Mat. 19. 6. And to be one fleſh by covenant, by troth plighted by Church-authority, which is the eſſentiall vnion, is the fundamentall cauſe of the <hi>ſignifying v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> which is the ring giuen in marriage, to ſignifie, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; wife are no more twaine, but one fleſh. Tis expreſſe Scripture, that tis granted to the Church to weare fine linnen, white and cleane. Rev. 19. 8. There is a ſimilitude betweene the triumphant and militant Church: and ſo an expreſſion of the ones glory by the others ſignification: and is it then contrary to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and order to <hi>weare the ſurpliſſe?</hi> Holy daies are contain'd in the Scripture: <hi>The Lords paſſeover,</hi> which we call Eaſter. Levit. 23. 5. <hi>The feaſt of vnlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened bread.</hi> Levit. 23. 6. <hi>The feast of firſt fruits,</hi> Lev. 23. 10. to the 24. verſe. <hi>The feaſt of Trumpets,</hi> Lev. 23. from 24 to the 34 verſe. <hi>The feast of Tabernacles. Mordecai had his Holy day,</hi> Heſt. 9. <hi>Iudeth had her Holy day.</hi> Iudeth 16. <hi>Macchabeus had his Holy day.</hi> Macchab. 1. 4. And ſeeing that <hi>Holy daies</hi> did not tranſgreſſe the fourth commandement before Chriſts comming; the Apoſtles <hi>Agapae,</hi> Feſtivall daies, and our Church-holy-daies, doe not tranſgreſſe that law. We ſhould bee very vnthankfull vnto God for the multiplying of his great mercies, if we did not ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely keepe them: the reaſon is ſhew'd before. <hi>In his rebus, de quib. nihil certi statuit ſcriptura divina, mos populi Dei, vel inſtituta maiorum pro lege tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſunt.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21422:20"/> D. Auguſt. Epiſt. 68. to <hi>Caſulanus.</hi> In thoſe things, which the Scripture hath not <hi>verbatim</hi> ſet downe: the cuſtomes of Gods people, or the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our Predeceſſors ought to bee receiued for lawes: ſo that they be deduced from Scriptures, and be not contrary to Scriptures; they are S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> limitations. Seeing then that the church hath autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity giuen her, let her exerciſe her authority. <hi>Let all things be done.</hi> For as long as the church is rul'd by Scripture, <hi>Shee is the pillar and ground of truth</hi> 1. Tim. 3. 15. to the vnlearned, to the catechiſed, to the vulgar vnderſtanding: then S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> being an infant in faith, beleeues, <hi>quia dixit Eccleſia,</hi> becauſe the church did teach him to beleeue. As long as the church is rul'd by Scriptures, <hi>Shee cannot erre, hell gates cannot prevaile againſt her,</hi> Mat. 16. 18. And therefore let all things be done decently &amp; in order, whatſoever our well reformed church commands <hi>to be done.</hi> Let the Prieſt weare the ſurpliſſe: let little children to be baptized, haue their <hi>Godfathers and Godmothers;</hi> let the baptized be ſigned with the ſigne of the <hi>Croſse.</hi> Let all communicants kneele reverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at receiuing the <hi>Lords Supper.</hi> Let all bow in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne aſſemblies at the name of IESVS. Let them that are to be married, be married with the <hi>Ring.</hi> Let <hi>Holy daies</hi> be kept: Let the Lord bee praiſed vpon <hi>Church Organs,</hi> and on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> and <hi>Holy daies,</hi> thus let him bee magnified with the muſicall ſound of all <hi>Church-bells.</hi> Let the dead be <hi>honorably buried.</hi> You haue a little booke of Articles, which containes
<pb facs="tcp:21422:20"/> ſeven generalls, all our church-traditions. The firſt is concerning the church-yard, Vicarage-houſe. The ſecond is concerning the Miniſterie, divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and Sacraments. The third is concerning Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Courts. The fourth concerning School-maſters. The fift concerning the pariſh clearke, and Sexton. The ſixt concerning the Pariſhioners. The ſeuenth concerning church-wardens &amp; Sides-men. Let all theſe things <hi>be done.</hi> For the doing of them well, doth honour God, and ſaue your owne ſoules. But if church-offenders are growne hard-hearted, ſtiffe-necked, ſtubborne, not to be reformed by neighbourly loue, good counſell, wholſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation: <hi>Dic Eccleſiae,</hi> tell the church. For all things muſt be done <hi>Decently, and in order,</hi> which is my fourth part of text.</p>
            <q>Decently and in order.</q>
            <p>Here is the manner, how Gods command firſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly how the churches command is to be obeyed, and this is <hi>Decently</hi> and in <hi>order:</hi> On the outſide by beauty, <hi>Decently,</hi> within and without according to rule, <hi>In order. Nihil peruerſo ordine, vel per conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, vel per inanem gloriam faciatis:</hi> ſo S. <hi>Hierome</hi> vpon theſe words: where there is perverſeneſſe, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwarting faction, there is noe church-decencie: factious contention, and vaine ſpirited glory is noe part of this church-order. <hi>Non temerè, non indecorè, non inſanè, ordine conueniente,</hi> ſo S. <hi>Chryſostome.</hi> Not raſhneſſe, not vnſeemelines, not diſtemper is the decency or order, that which is ſeemely, is church-decency,
<pb facs="tcp:21422:21"/> that which is conuenient is church-order. <hi>Omnia cum pace, &amp; diſciplinâ:</hi> ſo S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the peace of the church, this is church-decencie, the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the church, this is church order. The decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the church is oppoſite to <hi>vanity</hi> to <hi>ſordidneſse,</hi> to <hi>luxury.</hi> The order of the church is oppoſite to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and troubleſomeneſſe.</hi> ſoe <hi>Pareus.</hi> The decency of the church is, that Gods temple ſhould be all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, at leaſt very conuenient, that church-veſſells, and the materiall parts of the church be cleane, and comely: that the Prieſts veſtments be ſeemely: that all church actions publique, and priuate be void of lightneſſe, and ſuperſtition: that church-teachers, and hearers behaue themſelues with diuine grauity, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie and piety, as it becometh them, that ſtand in the preſence of God, and his holy Angells. Church order giues euery one his conuenient place, to ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, ſuperior places; to equalls, equall places; to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors, inferior places; to euery church-neceſſary a neceſſary place. Order obſerues church-time as well as church-place, and it ſtaies not there, but appoints who ſhall be church-teachers, and who ſhall be church-hearers, and to keepe both in order, there are appointed times to pray, to preach, to ſing pſalmes, to catechiſe, to communicate, to baptize. &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>caueatur, aedificatio eccleleſiae, &amp; ſingulorum maximè promoueatur:</hi> ſo <hi>Pareus.</hi> The tranſgreſſing of church-decencie, and order muſt be ſhun'd: the edifying of the church and of all in the church muſt be carefully obſerued. And we muſt goe a little farther: the <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21422:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>and honour of the Church</hi> muſt be carefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded: And wee muſt on a little farther. <hi>The able gratious practiſe of the Church</hi> muſt be preferred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all the edifying, beautifying, and externall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the church. S. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, that there is no church-decency, no church-order, where is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeneſſe, and diuiſion: and therefore Thomas Cartwright was noe true teacher of church decency, and order, let his 21 dangerous points of doctrine, and his one and fifty vntruths, falſifying of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, fathers of the church, Hiſtoriographers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther claſſicall Authors, be witneſſe: as 'tis obſerued by D <hi>Whitguift,</hi> in his booke againſt M. <hi>Cartwright.</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith where there is raſhnes, vnſeeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, diſtemper, that there is noe church-decencie, noe church order, and therefore the preciſe ones are noe teachers of church-decencie, and order: for they are raſh to thruſt that vpon vs for true religion, which began at the 250 yeare after Chriſt, and was put downe by the firſt Councell of Nice. S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith that there is church-decency, where is the peace, and the diſcipline of the church: for theſe are the well growne fruits of the Apoſtles doctrine: <hi>Let all things be done decently and in Order.</hi> There is church-decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, where is noe lightneſſe; and there is church-order, where is noe confuſion: and therefore frequenters of woods for churches haue noe church-decencie. For a ſuppoſe of their owne pates rings them a peale to frequent woods; that idolatrous Temples muſt never be frequented, if once idolatrous: and yet religion
<pb facs="tcp:21422:22"/> being reformed, thoſe temples (though once idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous) are againe to bee frequented to worſhip God with holy worſhip. So <hi>Calvin, Peter Martyr, Beza, Bucer,</hi> and B. <hi>Iewell.</hi> And to convert idolatrous tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples into chriſtian Temples was the practiſe of the Primitiue church at 179 yeare after <hi>Chriſt</hi> in king <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oius</hi> daies. There is no church-order, where is confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, where the ſame preacher, or teacher doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict one doctrine with an other, &amp; contradictions of doctrines are in <hi>Thomas Cartwright,</hi> as Doctor <hi>Whitguift</hi> hath obſerued. And there are contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and his fraternity: for there are 37 generall parts of doctrine, and 239 particular do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines in which one Romaniſt contradicts an other, as <hi>Pareus</hi> hath obſerued in his <hi>Irenicum.</hi> There is church-decency, where the church, and every part of the church is kept ſeemly. And there is church order, where ſuperiors are in ſuperior places, equalls in equal places, inferiors in inferior places. And there is no Church-decencie, where ruine, neglect, duſt, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe are Church-keepers: this is almoſt cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in theſe daies. A wood, a private conventicle, a factious ſect, I feare, is more ſolemnly frequented in many places in this land, than the Church of God. And there is no Church order, where Superiors are made inferiors, Kings to caſt their Crownes at the feet of Schiſmatiques, ſchiſmaticall Paſtors: yet thus M. <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> would haue it: And hee calls the Deane of a Cathedrall Church, the Canons, the Major, and Minor-Prebends, the Chauncellour, the
<pb facs="tcp:21422:22"/> Chaunter, the Piſtellers, and Goſpellers, hee vnman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly calls them all Abbi-lubbers. Thus what Church-order hath eſtabliſhed, hee with a word of diſgrace, would put downe againſt all order. There ſhould be decency and order obſeru'd in performing Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſhip, (which is the common prayers) And this is reprou'd by ſome, by others tis embrac'd, but tis with a running reverence: by others tis cut off in the middle to the diſhonour of God, and his Church: by others tis mumbled vp in an vnknowne tongue, as if Papiſts were vnwilling that all ſhould knowe what they ſay vnto God, yet every one had religion in his owne tongue, Act. 2. Tis decencie, and order, that we ſhould ſtand vp at the rehearſing of the Apoſtles Creed, to ſignifie, that wee doe, and will ſtand to our faith: but this ſtanding vp, ſome doe maliciouſly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and this ſtanding vp others doe vnwittingly neglect. The Font is the commanded place for bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, yet ſome doe baptize in Wells, in Brookes, in Rivers, &amp;c. to defend, to vphold a factious ſpirit. Tis decencie, and order to edifie the Church: but ſome care for no edifying. <hi>To beleeue as the Church beleeues</hi> this forme of words, is faith enough: and the beſt of that falſe beleeuing ſide, are afraid of eſſentiall and demonſtratiue expoſition; of the infallible rules of expoſition; the ſcripture being granted to be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly axiomaticall principle of faith. The learned rules of expoſition of Scriptures, which neither S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> nor any other father hath <hi>expreſso praecepto;</hi> theſe rules Papiſts dare not follow. Some reſpect onely
<pb facs="tcp:21422:23"/> the factious edifying, well known to the factious bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by oppoſing Church-decencie, and order. But beyond this edifying they neuer intend to proceed, like <hi>S. Pauls</hi> ſilly women, <hi>who are ever learning, but never able to come to the knowledge of the truth.</hi> And therefore the able gracious practiſe of the Church is neglected by them. A father of the Church muſt not be heard in his owne language, becauſe that ſpends time, and doth not edifie. And Church Organs the muſicall inſtruments of the Churches gracious prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, are tedious to them, becauſe they doe not edifie. To ring the Church-bells in peale on the Lords day, this the ſeparatiſts call profaning of the Sabbath. And tis their ignorance, being vnable to tell the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the worlds ſervile workes, which are forbidden by the fourth commaundement, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Churches muſicall works, which in their due time done, doe praiſe the Lord. Tis Church-decency, and Church-order, that the ſcriptures be taught lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, and grauely: but now the children of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets goe for Church-Doctors: and a Mechanicke, a preſuming ſpirit is receiued amongſt the Perfectiſts for a lawfull preacher, if their non-Eccleſiaſticall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit calls him: yet the Text faith, <hi>No man taketh this honour vnto himſelfe, but hee that is called of God, as was Aaron.</hi> Hebr. 5. 4. But one will obiect, what meanes all this diſcourſe, but to occaſion appearing of evill, and to giue offence to the weake brothers conſcience? Be not deceiued; here is no appearing of evill: no offence. Here is nothing, but Church-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency,
<pb facs="tcp:21422:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> and Church-order, which neither appeare evill nor are they any offence: for appearance of evill, and offence are oppoſite to theſe well governing and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying properties. And who are the weake brethren? <hi>Thomas Cartwrights</hi> Diſciples? In their conceipts there are none ſo godly, none ſo holy in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God. Thus farre I haue followed an vnſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a diſorderd company. This was the cauſe, that you ſhould knowe who are the vndecent, and the irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar in our Church, that you may avoid them. I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the decencie &amp; order of the church vnto you: and doe exhort you in the words of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> 1. Cor. 1. 10. <hi>Now I beſeech you brethren by the name of our Lord Ieſus Christ, that yee all ſpeake the ſame thing, &amp; that there be no diviſion among you, but that yee bee ioined perfectly together in the ſame minde, and in the ſame iudgement.</hi> And doe you aſſuredly beleeue that Non-conformiſts haue not the ſpirit of God to guid them. For they are the troubleſome inventers of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion. For whereas there is envying, and ſtrife, and diviſions among them, are they not carnall? While one ſaith, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> another I am of <hi>Apollo,</hi> whilſt they will heare none, but a diviſion making preacher, are they not carnall? <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>that they are carnall</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 3. 4. But I haue taught you better things, then to be carnall. Here is church-decency to cleanſe the Lords houſe, and to beautifie it: and therefore learne to be decent with church-decency. Here is church-order to ſet all things vniformely in Gods holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and therefore learne church-holy orders that you
<pb facs="tcp:21422:24"/> may be decent, and well-ordered Temples of the holy Ghoſt: that in this life you may ſo liue together <hi>in true faith, and religious charity;</hi> that in the world to come you may liue together in immortall glory. Which God for his infinite mercy grant vnto all through <hi>Christ Ieſus. To whom with the Father, and the holy Ghost, three perſons, and one immortall God be aſcribed all glory, honour, power, might, ſaluation, and thankeſgiving this day and for ever.</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21422:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
